Hello, welcome everybody. How is everybody doing today? This is going to be an
مرحباً، أهلاً وسهلاً بالجميع. كيف حالكم جميعاً اليوم؟ سيكون هذا درساً
awesome listening and speaking class. I'm so glad that all of you are here. Welcome
رائعاً في الاستماع والتحدث. أنا سعيدٌ جداً بحضوركم جميعاً. أهلاً
everybody. See the screen. All right. Now? Yes. Okay. So remember, good
وسهلاً بالجميع. أترون الشاشة؟ حسناً. الآن؟ نعم. حسناً. إذاً تذكروا، التواصل
communication starts with good listening, being an active listener means showing
الجيد يبدأ بالاستماع الجيد، أن تكون مستمعاً فعالاً يعني أن تُظهر
you're engaged. Sometimes we listen quickly for the main idea and that's our
أنك منخرطٌ ومشارك. أحياناً نستمع بسرعةٍ للفكرة الرئيسية وهذا هو تفكيرنا
fast and intuitive thinking and other times we need careful analytical
السريع والحدسي، وفي أحيانٍ أخرى نحتاج إلى استماعٍ تحليليٍّ
listening and that's when we really kind of pick things apart and try to
دقيق، وذلك عندما نقوم حقاً بتفكيك الأمور ونحاول
understand the deeper meaning of those things. So we need to practice both types
فهم المعنى الأعمق لتلك الأشياء. لذا نحتاج إلى ممارسة كلا النوعين
of listening to understand the superficial level of things in the meaning and
من الاستماع لفهم المستوى السطحي للأشياء في معناها
to understand (the) deeper analytical level of things. When you practice a lot, you get
ولفهم المستوى التحليلي الأعمق للأشياء. عندما تتدربون كثيراً،
the hang of it and you don't have to kind of deliberately seek to understand it
ستألفون الأمر ولن تضطروا إلى السعي عمداً لفهمه
so much. You'll just understand and it will become more intuitive with time but
إلى هذا الحد. ستفهمون ببساطة وسيصبح الأمر أكثر حدسية مع الوقت، ولكن
it's always good to analyze first. So we'll listen as the scenario is read
من الجيد دائماً التحليل أولاً. إذاً سنستمع بينما يُقرأ السيناريو
here. I want you to listen to it twice with different focuses and I'm trying to
هنا. أريدكم أن تستمعوا إليه مرتين بتركيزٍ مختلف، وأنا أحاول
show something that you might not understand. So don't feel bad if you don't. Okay.
أن أعرض شيئاً قد لا تفهمونه. لذا لا تشعروا بالسوء إذا لم تفعلوا. حسناً.
All right. Okay, team. For the new project, I need everyone to synergize their
حسناً. حسناً يا فريق. بالنسبة للمشروع الجديد، أحتاج من الجميع أن يوحدوا جهودهم (synergize)
deliverables by COB Tuesday and ensure proactive stakeholder engagement. Make it
في تسليماتهم (deliverables) بحلول نهاية دوام (COB) يوم الثلاثاء وأن يضمنوا مشاركة استباقية من أصحاب المصلحة.
snappy. Did you understand? The main idea, but there are some new words
أنجزوا الأمر بسرعة (Make it snappy). هل فهمتم؟ الفكرة الرئيسية، ولكن هناك بعض الكلمات الجديدة.
others are okay. Okay, so you have some experience which is great. You've got the
الأخرى لا بأس بها. حسناً، إذاً لديك بعض الخبرة وهذا رائع. لقد فهمت
main idea that we need to work together to get something done but there might
الفكرة الرئيسية وهي أننا بحاجة للعمل معاً لإنجاز شيء ما، ولكن قد يكون
be some things here that you don't understand. Which words are hard for you to
هناك بعض الأشياء هنا التي لا تفهمها. ما هي الكلمات التي تجد صعوبة في فهمها؟
understand? So the words that I don't understand are
الكلمات التي لا أفهمها هي
synergize and snappy. Okay, so to synergize something is basically to make
"synergize" و "snappy". حسناً، إذاً "synergize" لشيء ما يعني بشكل أساسي جعل الأشياء
things in sync, right? When things are synchronized, they're synergized. They
متزامنة (in sync)، أليس كذلك؟ عندما تكون الأشياء متزامنة، تكون "synergized" (متآزرة/متضافرة). إنها
work well together, right? So we need everybody to basically come together and
تعمل معاً بشكل جيد، أليس كذلك؟ لذا نحتاج من الجميع بشكل أساسي أن يجتمعوا
agree on what deliverables, what needs to be produced by Tuesday, and to make
ويتفقوا على التسليمات، أي ما يجب إنتاجه بحلول يوم الثلاثاء، و "make it snappy"
it snappy is to do it quickly. Oh, okay. When you're talking.
تعني أن تفعله بسرعة. أوه، حسناً. عندما تتحدث،
You're using that word, right? Oh, make it snappy.
أنت تستخدم تلك الكلمة، أليس كذلك؟ أوه، "أنجز الأمر بسرعة" (make it snappy).
All right. So let's listen to a short scenario and imagine you're in this
حسناً. إذاً دعونا نستمع إلى سيناريو قصير ونتخيل أنكم في هذا
this meeting. If you were to hear that in a meeting, what would you
الاجتماع. إذا سمعتم ذلك في اجتماع، ماذا كنتم
do to interrupt to try to understand? If you had some sort of question, you have
ستفعلون للمقاطعة ومحاولة الفهم؟ إذا كان لديكم نوع من الأسئلة، لقد فهمتم الفكرة الرئيسية، أليس كذلك؟
the main idea, right? But you wouldn't probably want to listen to what comes next a
ولكنكم ربما سترغبون في الاستماع إلى ما سيأتي بعد ذلك قليلاً.
little bit. How would you ask for clarification?
كيف ستطلبون توضيحاً؟
Well, as you mentioned, everything is about listening. So I think I will wait the
حسناً، كما ذكرتَ، كل شيء يتعلق بالاستماع. لذا أعتقد أنني سأنتظر الشخص
person to end what that person is (going to say)? And if I don't understand, then I will go
حتى ينهي ما (سيقوله)؟ وإذا لم أفهم، عندها سأذهب
and like, hey, I need clarification on this part of what I just say.
وأقول، اسمح لي، أحتاج إلى توضيح بشأن هذا الجزء مما قلته للتو.
So you would wait for the person to finish saying what they want to say.* And that's because
إذاً ستنتظر حتى ينهي الشخص قول ما يريد قوله.* وهذا لأنك
you don't want to be rude or interrupt anyone when they're talking. Yes. Actually, I always
لا تريد أن تكون وقحاً أو تقاطع أي شخص أثناء حديثه. نعم. في الواقع، أنا دائماً
tried to wait because you need to know what the person is thinking and not just to think like
أحاول الانتظار لأنك تحتاج إلى معرفة ما يفكر فيه الشخص وليس مجرد الاعتقاد بأن
that's what you're saying. So it's good not to make assumptions. I agree. And it's great to wait
هذا ما تقوله. نعم، من الجيد عدم وضع افتراضات. أتفق معك. ومن الرائع الانتظار
for those pauses in speech and conversation to know when we can ask for clarification.
لتلك الوقفات في الكلام والمحادثة لمعرفة متى يمكننا طلب توضيح.
Okay. So how do we interrupt politely? That's part of what we're talking about today.
حسناً. إذاً كيف نقاطع بأدب؟ هذا جزء مما نتحدث عنه اليوم.
Asking for clarity. They're useful phrases. Well, I would say, excuse me,
طلب التوضيح. هناك عبارات مفيدة. حسناً، سأقول، عفواً،
what's like, that would be a good example.
ماذا يعني، سيكون ذلك مثالاً جيداً.
So I will say, excuse me, I just would like to know what you are trying to say when you are
لذا سأقول، عفواً، أود فقط أن أعرف ماذا تقصد عندما تتحدث
talking about this contract or something like that. Okay. So I need more clarification on these
عن هذا العقد أو شيء من هذا القبيل. حسناً. لذا أحتاج إلى مزيد من التوضيح حول هذه الموضوعات.
subjects. All right. It's very formal. I like that.
حسناً. هذا رسمي جداً. يعجبني ذلك.
Yes, we need to... that's like our environment when we talk with we have our meetings.
نعم، نحن بحاجة إلى... هذا يشبه بيئتنا عندما نتحدث في اجتماعاتنا.
We can make* jokes outside, you know, but then we are with the meeting where we need to try to be
يمكننا المزاح* في الخارج، كما تعلم، ولكن عندما نكون في الاجتماع، نحتاج إلى محاولة أن نكون
a really like professional. You can be more casual outside of the meeting, but in the meeting
محترفين حقاً. يمكنك أن تكون أكثر عفوية خارج الاجتماع، ولكن في الاجتماع
itself, it's time to be professional and formal. All right. So this language register is really
نفسه، حان الوقت لتكون محترفاً ورسمياً. حسناً. إذاً هذا السجل اللغوي حقاً
a bit formal and also intonation is important. You know, sounds rise and they fall too. So an
رسمي بعض الشيء وكذلك التنغيم مهم. كما تعلم، الأصوات ترتفع وتنخفض أيضاً. لذا
example would be sorry. Could you please repeat the part about COB or could you repeat the part
مثال على ذلك هو، آسف. هل يمكنك من فضلك تكرار الجزء المتعلق بـ COB؟ أو هل يمكنك تكرار الجزء
about making it snappy? What does that mean? All right. So now notice that we use could here and could
المتعلق بـ "أنجز الأمر بسرعة" (making it snappy)؟ ماذا يعني ذلك؟ حسناً. الآن لاحظوا أننا استخدمنا "could" هنا و "could"
is considered more polite than can. So could is a little bit more formal and then can is a little
تعتبر أكثر أدباً من "can". لذا "could" أكثر رسمية قليلاً ثم "can" أكثر
bit more casual, although you can use either one. Someone is not being disrespectful if they use can,
عفوية قليلاً، على الرغم من أنه يمكنك استخدام أي منهما. لا يعتبر الشخص غير محترم إذا استخدم "can"،
but if you want to show more formality, it's better to use could. Here's another example.
ولكن إذا كنت تريد إظهار المزيد من الرسمية، فمن الأفضل استخدام "could". إليكم مثال آخر.
This time I would like for you to try to raise the intonation at the end. So is that right?
هذه المرة أود منكم محاولة رفع التنغيم في النهاية. مثلاً، "هل هذا صحيح؟" (Is that right?)
All right. Is that right? Can you, can you read this part here?
حسناً. "هل هذا صحيح؟" هل يمكنك، هل يمكنك قراءة هذا الجزء هنا؟
If I understand correctly, you're asking us to, is that right?
إذا فهمت بشكل صحيح، فأنت تطلب منا أن...، هل هذا صحيح؟
Is that right? Yeah. And here's another example. We're working a lot. Is that right?
هل هذا صحيح؟ نعم. وإليكم مثال آخر. نحن نعمل كثيراً. هل هذا صحيح؟
We have to come in this weekend. Is that right? All right. How about this one? Can you read
يجب أن نأتي في نهاية هذا الأسبوع. هل هذا صحيح؟ حسناً. ماذا عن هذا؟ هل يمكنك أن تقرأ
this one for us? Could you please explain what you mean by snappy?
هذا لنا؟ هل يمكنك من فضلك أن تشرح ماذا تقصد بـ "snappy"؟
Uh-huh. Very good. Hi, snappy. Well, snappy means it should be different.
أهأ. جيد جداً. مرحباً، "snappy". حسناً، "snappy" تعني أن يكون سريعاً وحيوياً.
Well, no, I think that's fine. We can use, for example, like the one you said COB because
حسناً، لا، أعتقد أن هذا جيد. يمكننا استخدام، على سبيل المثال، مثل الذي قلته COB لأن
there are some people* that don't know what COB means. You could just simply ask, could you
هناك بعض الأشخاص* الذين لا يعرفون ماذا تعني COB. يمكنك ببساطة أن تسأل، هل يمكنك
tell me what snappy means? I don't know this. It's a new word for me, you could say.
أن تخبرني ماذا تعني "snappy"؟ أنا لا أعرف هذا. إنها كلمة جديدة بالنسبة لي، يمكنك القول.
You know, I think sometimes we feel embarrassed when we don't know something.
كما تعلمون، أعتقد أننا أحياناً نشعر بالحرج عندما لا نعرف شيئاً ما.
And so we don't want to ask, we don't want to admit, but it's okay to clarify.
لذا لا نريد أن نسأل، لا نريد أن نعترف، ولكن لا بأس في طلب التوضيح.
The whole purpose of communication and business is to understand and be understood.
الغرض الكامل من التواصل والأعمال هو أن تَفهَم وأن تُفهَم.
And a key takeaway from this slide here is basically we use could to make polite requests.
والنقطة الرئيسية من هذه الشريحة هنا هي أننا بشكل أساسي نستخدم "could" لتقديم طلبات مهذبة.
You can use discourse markers like excuse me or if I understand correctly you're asking
يمكنك استخدام علامات الخطاب مثل "Excuse me" أو "If I understand correctly, you're asking..." أو "you're telling us that's right"
or you're telling us that's right and then rephrasing what they say. Those are really great ways to
ثم إعادة صياغة ما يقولونه. هذه طرق رائعة حقاً
ask for clarification. All right. So go ahead, I'm sorry.
لطلب التوضيح. حسناً. إذاً تفضل، أنا آسف.
No, maybe before I didn't use to do that, but now like I feel more confident to ask for
لا، ربما في السابق لم أكن أفعل ذلك، ولكن الآن أشعر بثقة أكبر في السؤال عن معنى الكلمة،
the meaning of the word, to (know) what they're saying. So we know what they're exactly there trying
لمعرفة ما يقولونه. لذا نعرف بالضبط ما يحاولون إيصاله.
to communicate. Yeah... it only gets better with time.
نعم... الأمر يتحسن مع الوقت فقط.